The Max Kowalski Collection
Yale University Music Library
The Max Kowalski Collection
1913-1939
Misc. Ms. 293
Yale University Music Library
0.25
(5 folders)
Vocal music by the Polish-German-English composer Max Kowalski (1882-1956)
Kowalski, Max, 1882-1956
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Max Kowalski Collection was established in the Music Library of Yale University in 1989.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by uniform title.
Scope and Contents
The Max Kowalski Collection consists of holograph scores for 13 of Kowalski's Lieder, including 1 of the 12 Gedichte aus Pierrot Lunaire, 3 of the 6 Heine-Lieder, and 9 of the 12 Lieder on texts by Li Po. The collection also holds a printed score of the composer's Lieder, op. 17, published by Universal Edition in 1934.
Biographical / Historical
Max Kowalski was born in Kowal, Poland on August 10, 1882. A year later he moved to Germany, where he was educated; in addition to his musical studies (composition with Bernhard Sekles and singing with Alexander Heinemann), he earned a law degree from the University of Marburg. As a singer-composer, Kowalski naturally specialized in the composition of Lieder. Under the Nazi regime, he was imprisoned in Buchenwald, but he was released in 1939. He then moved to England, where he remained until his death in London on June 4, 1956.
Songs with piano; Giraud, Albert, 1860-1929 -- Musical settings; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 -- Musical settings; Heine, Heinrich, 1797-1856 -- Musical settings; Kowalski, Max, 1882-1956; Li, Bai, 701-762 -- Musical settings
- Inventory (Box 1, Folder 1)
- [Gedichte aus Pierrot Lunaire. Heimfahrt] Heimfahrt aus Pierrot Lunaire von Albert Giraud / Deutsch von Otto Erich Hartleben; komponiert von Max Kowalski., 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  General
  Holograph, signed, in ink.
  For voice and piano.
  German words.
  Markings in pencil.
  Cover stamped: Opernsänger/HANS ASSENHEIM/Konzertsänger/Oratoriensänger
- [Lieder, Op. 17] Sechs Lieder aus dem westöstlichen Divan von Goethe, op. 17 / Max Kowalski. -- Wien: Universal, c1934, 1 score (12 p.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- [Lieder (1937). Der Tod, das ist die kühle Nacht] Der Tod, das ist die kühle Nacht / von Heine; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 23 Mai 1937, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Erasures.
  Cover stamped: Opernsänger/HANS ASSENHEIM/Konzertsänger
- [Lieder (1937). Ein schöner Stern geht auf in meiner Nacht] Ein schöner Stern geht auf in meiner Nacht von Heine / komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 6 Juni 1937, 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Erasures and corrections in pencil.
- [Lieder (1937). Mir träumte einst von wildem Liebesglühn] Mir träumte einst von wildem Liebesglühn von Heine / komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 6.XII.1937, 1 manuscript score (4 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Cover stamped: Opernsänger/HANS ASSENHEIM/Konzertsänger/(Mitglied des Reichsver-/bandes d. jud. Kultur/bünde in Deutschland)
- [Lieder (1939). Auf der Wiese] Auf der Wiese von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 12.XII.1939, 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Beim vollen Becher] Beim vollen Becher von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 24.XII.1939, 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Beständigen] Die Beständigen von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 7.6.38, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Ferne Flöte] Die ferne Flöte von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 20.XII.1939, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Im Boot] Im Boot von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 14.XI.1939, 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Improvisation] Improvisation von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 19.XII.1939, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Lingende Gespenster] Lingende Gespenster von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 21.XII.1939, 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Selbstvergessenheit] Selbstvergessenheit von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 24.VII.1938, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [Lieder (1939). Silberreiher] Der Silberreiher von Li-tai-pe / aus dem Chinesischen übertragen von Klabund; komponiert von Max Kowalski. -- 30.XI.1939, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)